[
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Which one is an oil yielding plant among the following?</H3>",
        "options": ["Lentil", "Sunflower", "Cauliflower", "Hibiscus"],
        "correctAnswer": 1
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Which one is not a source of carbohydrate?</H3>",
        "options": ["Rice", "Millets", "Sorghum", "Gram"],
        "correctAnswer": 3
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Find out the wrong statement from the following</H3>",
        "options": ["White revolution is meant for increase in milk production", "Blue revolution is meant for increase in fish production",
                    "Increasing food production without compromising with environmental quality is called as sustainable agriculture", "None of the above"],
        "correctAnswer": 3
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> To solve the food problem of the country, which among the following is necessary?</H3>",
        "options": ["Increased production and storage of food grains", "Easy access of people to the food grain", "People should have money to purchase the grains",
                    "All of the above"],
        "correctAnswer": 3
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Find out the correct sentence. <BR> (i) Hybridisation means crossing between genetically dissimilar plants <BR> (ii) Cross between two varieties is called as inter specific hybridisation <BR> (iii) Introducing genes of desired character into a plant gives genetically modified crop <BR> (iv) Cross between plants of two species is called as inter varietal hybridisation</H3>",
        "options": ["(i) and (iii)", "(ii) and (iv)", "(ii) and (iii)", "(iii) and (iv)"],
        "correctAnswer": 0
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Weeds affect the crop plants by</H3>",
        "options": ["killing of plants in field before they grow", "dominating the plants to grow", "competing for various resources of crops (plants) causing low availability of nutrients", "all of the above."],
        "correctAnswer": 2
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Which one of the following species of honey bee is an Italian species?</H3>",
        "options": ["Apis dorsata", "Apis florae", "Apis cerana indica", "Apis mellifera"],
        "correctAnswer": 3
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Find out the correct sentence about manure.<br>(i) Manure contains large quantities of organic matter and small quantities of nutrients.<br>(ii) It increases the water holding capacity of sandy soil.<br>(iii) It helps in draining out of excess of water from clayey soil.<br>(iv) Its excessive use pollutes environment because it is made of animal excretory waste.</H3>",
        "options": ["(i) and (iii)", "(i) and (ii)", "(ii) and (iii)", "(iii) and (iv)"],
        "correctAnswer": 1
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Cattle husbandry is done for the following purposes <br>(i) Milk Production<br>(ii) Agricultural work<br>(iii) Meat production<br>(iv) Egg production</H3>",
        "options": ["(i), (ii) and (iii)", "(ii), (iii) and (iv)", "(iii) and (iv)", "(i) and (iv)"],
        "correctAnswer": 0
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Which of the following are Indian cattle?<br>(i) Bos indicus<br>(ii) Bos domestica<br>(iii) Bos bubalis<br>(iv) Bos vulgaris</H3>",
        "options": ["(i) and (iii)", "(i) and (ii)", "(ii) and (iii)", "(iii) and (iv)"],
        "correctAnswer": 0
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Which of the following are exotic breeds?<br>(i) Brawn<br>(ii) Jersey<br>(iii) Brown Swiss<br>(iv) Jersey Swiss</H3>",
        "options": ["(i) and (iii)", "(ii) and (iii)", "(i) and (iv)", "(ii) and (iv)"],
        "correctAnswer": 1
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Poultry farming is undertaken to raise following<br>(i) Egg production<br>(ii) Feather production<br>(iii) Chicken meat<br>(iv) Milk production</H3>",
        "options": ["(i) and (iii)", "(i) and (ii)", "(ii) and (iii)", "(iii) and (iv)"],
        "correctAnswer": 0
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Poultry fowl are susceptible to the following pathogens</H3>",
        "options": ["Viruses", "Bacteria", "Fungi", "All of the above"],
        "correctAnswer": 3
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Which one of the following fishes is a surface feeder?</H3>",
        "options": ["Rohus", "Mrigals", "Common carps", "Catlas"],
        "correctAnswer": 3
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Animal husbandry is the scientific management of<br>(i) animal breeding<br>(ii) culture of animals<br>(iii) animal livestock<br>(iv) rearing of animals</H3>",
        "options": ["(i), (ii) and (iii)", "(ii), (iii) and (iv)", "(i), (ii) and (iv)", "(i), (iii) and (iv)"],
        "correctAnswer": 3
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Which one of the following nutrients is not available in fertilizers?</H3>",
        "options": ["Nitrogen", "Phosphorus", "Iron", "Potassium"],
        "correctAnswer": 2
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "<H3>[<I>Chapter: Improvement in Food Resources</I>]<br> Preventive and control measures adopted for the storage of grains include</H3>",
        "options": ["strict cleaning", "proper disjoining", "fumigation", "all of the above"],
        "correctAnswer": 3
    }
]
